<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prophylaktikon, or, Some considerations of a notable expedient to root out the French pox from the English nation with excellent defensive remedies to preserve mankind from the infection of pocky women : also an advertisement, wherein is discover'd the dangerous practices of ignorant pretenders to the cure of the disease / by L.S., Dr. of physick.</title>
            <author>L. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58573</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S112</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29344</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11076955</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11076955</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46270</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58573)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46270)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1431:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prophylaktikon, or, Some considerations of a notable expedient to root out the French pox from the English nation with excellent defensive remedies to preserve mankind from the infection of pocky women : also an advertisement, wherein is discover'd the dangerous practices of ignorant pretenders to the cure of the disease / by L.S., Dr. of physick.</title>
                  <author>L. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 86 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title of work is in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Syphilis.</term>
               <term>Sexually transmitted diseases --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46270:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46270:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Προφυλακτικὸν OR, Some Conſideration OF A Notable Expedient To root out the FRENCH POX From the <hi>Engliſh Nation.</hi> With Excellent Defenſive Remedies TO Preſerve Mankind from the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>POCKY</hi> Women.</p>
            <p>Alſo an <hi>Advertiſement,</hi> wherein is diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd the dangerous Practices of <hi>Ignorant Pretenders</hi> to the <hi>Cure</hi> of this <hi>Diſeaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>L. S.</hi> Dr. of Phyſick.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>Demoſt. ad Laidem.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year. 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:46270:2"/>
            <head>The Printer to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>BE pleaſed to take notice, that the</hi> Doctor <hi>has lately left his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Habitation, and for the more</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate reception <hi>of his Patients, lives now in</hi> Hyde-Street <hi>near</hi> Blooms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury-Market; <hi>the Houſe he lives in is near the Sign of the</hi> Clock, <hi>and has a Porch with Rails before the door.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:46270:2"/>
            <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT To all Perſons concern'd in the POX.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have ſpent ſome years in ſtudying to help you in this <hi>important Affair.</hi> And ſurely I may (without any breach of Modeſty) pretend to ſome skill in this Buſineſs as well as my Neighbours. For I have perus'd no leſs than three hundred ſixty and eight Authors, who have learnedly treated of this Diſeaſe. I have tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd alſo, and conſulted ſome prime Phyſicians abroad, and carefully remarqu'd the Secrets of their Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. I have had plentiful Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the worſt of Patients, <hi>i. e.</hi> thoſe who have been ſpoyl'd by <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanks</hi> and <hi>unskilful Surgeons,</hi> and alſo forlorn, deſpair'd of, and
<pb facs="tcp:46270:3"/>quite given over by <hi>learned Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> Many of theſe <hi>unfortun<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ate Perſons</hi> by my Care have been in a ſhort time reſtor'd to perfect health; but ſome have periſhed: and indeed (if Miracles are not to be expected) how could it be otherwiſe? the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural parts were ſo corrupted, the Bones ſo carious and rotten, and the whole <hi>Compages</hi> of the Body ſo rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and deſperate, that none but an <hi>Apollo</hi> could promiſe either to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or the Patient any real perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon a Diſeaſe in thoſe deſperate Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>I have diligently compar'd what I read in Authors with what I daily obſerv'd in my own Patients, and remarqu'd in the Practice of others: out of all which I have compil'd a <hi>Treatiſe of the Pox,</hi> fully ſhewing its Fſſence, Origin, Cauſes, Diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, Symptoms, Signs, and Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticks, with all the ſeveral Wayes of Care now in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe. This Treatiſe
<pb facs="tcp:46270:3"/>I have finiſh'd, and keep by me rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for the <hi>Preſs,</hi> expecting only ſome ſpare time for the ſetting out a Work of that high Concern. But, as <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius</hi> relates of the furious <hi>Caligu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> who being weary'd in butchering Mankind by Parcels, wiſh'd all the people of <hi>Rome</hi> had but one neck, that he might diſpatch them at a Blow: So in my <hi>Treatiſe of the Pox,</hi> my endeavours were againſt the Pox in particular perſons only, but in this enſuing Tractate I have laid the Ax to the root, and given it ſuch a <hi>fatal Blow,</hi> that in a ſhort time this Nation may be ſecur'd from any Attaques of that <hi>Filthy Diſeaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I well fore-ſee that a Treatiſe of this Nature will not be well reſented by All. For ſome formal Perſons will endeavour to miſ-repreſent the <hi>Charitable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign</hi> of this <hi>Work,</hi> and alledge, that the <hi>Pox</hi> is a <hi>beaſtly Diſeaſe,</hi> which few or none have, but ſuch as well
<pb facs="tcp:46270:4"/>deſerve it; and that the <hi>Obſcenity</hi> of it is the cauſe why <hi>Eminent Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians</hi> meddle not with it, but have hitherto left the buſineſs wholly to <hi>Surgeons, Barbers, Tooth-drawers,</hi> and <hi>Mountebanks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 'Tis confeſs'd, that the <hi>Pox</hi> is a <hi>naſty Diſeaſe.</hi> But, does it therefore follow, that the <hi>Cure</hi> is to be manag'd only by <hi>Tooth-drawers, Mountebanks,</hi> and <hi>Empiriques?</hi> Or, that 'tis below the Concern of an <hi>Eminent Phyſician</hi> to meddle in this Caſe? For my part I never yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, that 'twas any Crime in a Phyſician to help Mankind in <hi>fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Diſeaſes,</hi> but rather that 'twas an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking which ought to be cheriſh'd and countenanc'd by all good Men. The more loathſome the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, the more <hi>Commiſeration</hi> is requir'd, and the Phyſician is oblig'd to a more tender Care. I will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, that my Intentions in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piling this Tractate, were Modeſt
<pb facs="tcp:46270:4"/>and Good; not to countenance De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery, but to root out this Exotic Plant, and defend Innocent Perſons from the Fury of a Cruel Diſeaſe. I will faithfully promiſe you, that the enſuing Diſcourſe ſhall be manag'd with all the Modeſty and Civility of Expreſſion imaginable, ſo that the <hi>oculi emiſſitii</hi> (as <hi>Plautus</hi> phraſes it) of <hi>Envy</hi> it ſelf ſhall not be able to finde any Offence in that kind.</p>
            <p>This <hi>foul Diſeaſe</hi> is a complicate Evil, and as it were a Combination of the worſt of Diſeaſes, advanc'd to a ſtrange degree of Malignity. And as its <hi>Effects</hi> are <hi>moſt dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> and <hi>terrible,</hi> ſo alſo is the <hi>Cure abſtruſe, arduous,</hi> and <hi>difficult,</hi> and not to be attempted by that <hi>Illiterate Rabble</hi> of <hi>Mountebanks, Tooth-drawers,</hi> and <hi>Ignoramuſſes,</hi> who in three dayes may do you more hurt, than you ſhall ever claw off while you breath, You are therefore carefully
<pb facs="tcp:46270:5"/>to avoid thoſe Perſons as Enemies to Mankind, Men full of <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Promiſes,</hi> but without any <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance</hi> at all. We daily ſee and lament the <hi>ſignal Miſcarriages</hi> of theſe Men; how Thouſands eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Year loſe their <hi>Lives,</hi> and Ten thouſands their <hi>Noſes.</hi> And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in one Month the Malignity might be carry'd off, and the Diſeaſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly cur'd, theſe men by their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous handling the Diſeaſe do ſo affix it to the Patient, and ſo root it in his bones, that 'tis afterwards im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be remov'd. Be wary therefore, and keep out of the Talons of theſe <hi>Harpyies,</hi> who uſe many <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices</hi> and <hi>Inſinuations</hi> to draw you in. You are to addreſs to <hi>learned Phyſicians</hi> and expert <hi>Chirurg.</hi> for help in this Caſe. For let me tell you, There's ſcarce one among a hundred of thoſe who profeſs <hi>this Cure</hi> that throughly underſtand the Nature of the Diſeaſe, the Cauſe of its Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms,
<pb facs="tcp:46270:5"/>or any <hi>ready</hi> or <hi>certain Way</hi> of <hi>Cure.</hi> And this is the reaſon ſo many periſh of the <hi>Pox,</hi> who might eaſily have been cur'd had they fallen into the hands of <hi>skilful Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I have one thing more to acquaint you with, and it is this, ſeveral Doctors in this Town ſeeing the admirable Effects of my <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes</hi> and <hi>Bezoartiques</hi> upon the <hi>worſt</hi> and moſt <hi>profound Poxes,</hi> have with ſome importunity ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me to a <hi>Diſcovery.</hi> But I have not as yet diſcover'd them to any. Not, that I ſhould be backward in any thing which might in the leaſt promote or advance the <hi>Publique Good:</hi> but this <hi>Expedite way of Curing the Pox</hi> (which was not wholly of my own Invention, but in part communicated by thoſe excellent Phyſicians <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de Bodé</hi> and <hi>Monſieur Balon</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> the moſt skilful, not only of <hi>France,</hi> but of all Chriſtendome, in
<pb facs="tcp:46270:6"/>the <hi>Expedite</hi> and <hi>happy Cure</hi> of <hi>this Diſeaſe</hi>) I am unwilling to put into the hands of ſome few to be monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz'd, and made uſe of for their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> only, becauſe I have deſign'd a <hi>Diſcovery</hi> to all, and to print them for the benefit of the whole Nation.</p>
            <p>This little Tractate therefore is but a fore-runner of a <hi>greater</hi> and <hi>more Elaborate Work.</hi> For I do intend (if God ſpare my Life, and proſper my Endeavours) very ſuddenly to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the World with ſome <hi>remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Obſervations</hi> and <hi>Secrets</hi> in this Diſeaſe; and alſo put the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> and <hi>Surgeons</hi> of this Age in a <hi>New Way</hi> of <hi>Curing</hi> the <hi>Pox,</hi> far more <hi>Expedite, Certain,</hi> and <hi>Safe</hi> than any bitherto known to the World. But in the mean time I conjure and charge you once again to beware of <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanks,</hi> and the <hi>Illiterate Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> of <hi>Pretenders</hi> to this <hi>Cure.</hi> Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>L. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46270:6"/>
            <head>A Notable Expedient to root out the <hi>POX.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> A Summary Account of the Pox. Its Names. Which moſt proper. French Pox and Lues Venerea diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allow'd. Aloys. Luiſinas noted. Anti-venereal Medicaments what. The Pox not an Epidemic Diſeaſe, againſt Leonicenus, Fracaſtorius and Maſſa. Not a New and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Diſeaſe. Shown to be Sporadic here, and Endemial in the W. Indies.</head>
               <p>THis <hi>Calamitous Diſeaſe</hi> has many Names, ſome whereof we paſs by, as being phantaſtic
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46270:7"/>and affected; or barbarous and blaſphemous. The moſt apt Names are <hi>Morbus Indicus, Hiſpanicus vel Neapolitanus:</hi> but the moſt uſual is the <hi>French Pox.</hi> For moſt Nations in <hi>Europe</hi> commonly uſe that <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation.</hi> And <hi>Leo Africanus</hi> (<hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrip. Afric. lib.</hi> 1.) aſſures us, 'tis ſo called in many parts of <hi>Africa,</hi> as at <hi>Tunis</hi> in <hi>Barbary,</hi> and in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> as alſo in <hi>Syria</hi> in <hi>Aſia:</hi> &amp; that the <hi>Mahometans</hi> uſual. Imprecati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, <hi>Te Morbus malè perdat Galli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</hi> But methinks, 'tis pity to affix the Title on the <hi>French</hi> and rob the <hi>Italians</hi> of that Honour; becauſe 'twas firſt brought from the <hi>Indies</hi> by <hi>Columbus</hi> an <hi>Italian,</hi> and at <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> firſt ſhew'd it ſelf to Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and at this day is more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in <hi>Italy</hi> than in any other Country in <hi>Europe,</hi> as is generally atteſted by <hi>Italian</hi> Phyſicians them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. But eſpecially becauſe ſome <hi>Italians</hi> ſeem to glory in it. <hi>Hier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Mercurialis</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:46270:7"/>an <hi>Italian</hi> Phyſician (<hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>de Morbo Gallico</hi>) ſayes, <hi>Ideo laus eſt Italorum ut abundent hoe morbo, quia indulgent Veneri &amp; utuntur paſſim mulieribus infectis, ut non mirum ſit eſſe peculiarem morbum noſtrarum plagarum.</hi> And they tell us, That ſince the Pox has been ſo familiar with them, it has done them a double Kindneſs; for,</p>
               <p n="1">1. It has in good part freed them from the <hi>Plague,</hi> for ſince the <hi>Pox</hi> came among them, they are ſeldom troubled with the <hi>Teſt,</hi> whereas in former Ages 'twas far more fierce and frequent than it has been ſince.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They obſerve that ſince they had the <hi>Pox,</hi> the <hi>Leproſy</hi> has almoſt left them, ſo that now eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Lazaretto</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> is filled with <hi>Neapolitans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some others in complement to the <hi>French</hi> forbear the <hi>Vulgar Name,</hi> and call it <hi>Lues Venerea.</hi> But though their Civility deſerves Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46270:8"/>yet this Denomination can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be allow'd. For <hi>Lues,</hi> as <hi>Iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus</hi> obſerves (<hi>Orig. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.) is the <hi>Plague</hi> or a <hi>Peſtilential</hi> and <hi>Epidemic Diſeaſe.</hi> And as <hi>Feſtus</hi> ſayes, <hi>Lues eſt diluens uſque ad nihil, tractum à Graeco</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. So in the judgment of all who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Propriety of Words, <hi>Lues</hi> denotes an <hi>Epidemic</hi> or <hi>Peſtilential Diſeaſe,</hi> proceeding from a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cauſe, and killing the greater part of thoſe who receive Infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But the Pox is not an <hi>Epide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mic</hi> but <hi>Sporadic Diſeaſe;</hi> 'tis not received from any common Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the Air, but by Contact of infected Bodies. Again, <hi>Lues,</hi> or the <hi>Peſt,</hi> deſtroyes the greater part of the Infected: but moſt of thoſe who have the Pox live, and may be cur'd. And laſtly, <hi>Lues</hi> is an <hi>Acute Diſeaſe,</hi> but the <hi>Pox</hi> is <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic.</hi> 2. Nor can it properly be term'd <hi>Venerea.</hi> For that ſignifies
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46270:8"/>a Diſeaſe received by the uſe of <hi>Venery.</hi> But this Diſeaſe is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes got by <hi>Venus:</hi> for Children get it by ſucking Infectious Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; and Nurſes often receive it from infected Infants. And moſt Phyſicians tell us 'tis to be got by profuſe kiſſing of women who have <hi>Pockie <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers</hi> in their Mouths: as alſo by lying in the ſheets wherein <hi>Neapolitans</hi> have ſweat. That therefore's an unſufferable <hi>Capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chio</hi> in <hi>Aloyſius Luiſinus,</hi> who calls his Collection of Authors who have writ of the <hi>Pox</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as if <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Venus</hi> and the <hi>Pox</hi> were one and the ſame <hi>Identic</hi> thing. I wiſh Dr. <hi>H.</hi> would conſider the Title of his Book, <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus unmaskt.</hi> Thoſe alſo fall into the ſame Errour, who call their <hi>Medicines</hi> againſt the Pox <hi>Anti-ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nereal Remedies.</hi> For an <hi>Antivene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Medicine,</hi> according to the true import of the word, is that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46270:9"/>which is given to luxurious perſons to repreſs the furious deſires of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus:</hi> as thoſe <hi>Aque Caſtitatis</hi> ſo often mentioned in Authors, but eſpecially when they treat of <hi>Furor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>terinus.</hi> Alſo <hi>Anti-venereal</hi> may ſignify thoſe <hi>Magic Compoſitions</hi> uſed by <hi>Sorcerers</hi> to diſable marry'd Perſons from <hi>Venus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phyſicians</hi> differ about the <hi>Origin</hi> of the Pox: for, 1. Some hold it to be an <hi>Epidemic</hi> Diſeaſe, and by conſequence to proceed from a <hi>Common cauſe:</hi> and of this Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is <hi>Leonicenus, Fracaſtorius, Nic. Maſſa</hi> and ſome others. But yet theſe men differ about this <hi>Common Cauſe;</hi> for ſome hold it to be a <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lign Influence</hi> deriv'd from a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of <hi>Saturn, Mars</hi> and <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> &amp;c. And this is the Opinion of <hi>Maſſa</hi> in his Book of the <hi>Pox.</hi> But <hi>Leonicenus</hi> will have it to be a great Inundation of <hi>Tyber</hi> in <hi>P. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexanders</hi> time, which drowned the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46270:9"/>greateſt part of <hi>Rome,</hi> and corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Air: from whence he ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines the <hi>Pox</hi> to have had its firſt Beginning. And this he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to confirm by telling us, that in <hi>P. Pelagius</hi>'s time <hi>Tyber</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow'd his banks, and upon that Inundation preſently enſu'd the <hi>Peſt</hi> and a ſtrange <hi>ill-natur'd Scab</hi> or <hi>Mangineſs,</hi> which the Phyſicians of that age could not cure. And he ſayes the like happen'd in <hi>P. Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nif.</hi> 4th's dayes alſo.</p>
               <p>Here two things are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marqu'd: 1. That 'tis probable the Favourers of this Opinion firſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Pox <hi>Lues Ven.</hi> ſuppoſing it a <hi>General Epidemic Diſeaſe</hi> proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from a <hi>Common Cauſe.</hi> 2. That theſe men were of opinion it would in time <hi>ſeneſcere,</hi> decay, and be quite antiquated, as other <hi>Epidemic Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers</hi> are.</p>
               <p>But the Reaſons offered by <hi>Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt.</hi> and his <hi>Partizans</hi> have not at
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46270:10"/>all ſatisfy'd the world, or convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced us that 'tis <hi>Epidemic,</hi> or, that it will in future Ages abandon theſe parts of the World. For, 1. We have no Reaſon to believe it <hi>Epidemic,</hi> or, to proceed from a <hi>Common Cauſe,</hi> as the pernicious Influence of Stars, or Corruption of Air; becauſe Diſeaſes proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from ſuch Cauſes never conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue long, but when the bad Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is at an End, and the Air freed from that adventitious venemous quality, they end alſo: But the Pox has continued ſome Ages, and with as much fierceneſs as ever. Nor, 2. have we any Grounds to believe (as ſome endeavour to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us) that the Pox does de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline, and by degrees abate of its former Fury: for our daily Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation tells us the contrary, and that 'tis to the full as fierce and formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as ever.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Some others affirm the <hi>Pox</hi> to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46270:10"/>be a <hi>New</hi> and <hi>Extraordinary Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe,</hi> ſent by Heaven as a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the <hi>extravagant Luſts</hi> of Mankind. And theſe men are ſo far from believing as the others, <hi>viz.</hi> That it does decline and abate of its former fury, and will in time abandon theſe parts, that on the contrary they think it advanced to a higher Degree of Malignity, and attended with crueller Symptoms than 'twas in the beginning. <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> not only thinks it will conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to the end of the world, but fears that in a matter of 80 years 'twill infect all Mankind. <hi>Et for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitan, quod Deus avertat,</hi> 80. <hi>aut pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo plurium annorum ſpacio omnem hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manam progeniem invaſura.</hi> (de Morb. occ. &amp; ven. lib. 5. cap. 11.) And a certain <hi>London Phyſician</hi> has aſſerted that all this Nation has a <hi>Touch</hi> of the <hi>Pox</hi> and <hi>Scurvy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The Third Opinion is of thoſe wo affirm the Pox with us to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46270:11"/>be a <hi>Sporadic Diſeaſe</hi> receiv'd only by contact of infectious bodies: but in ſome part of the <hi>Weſt Indies</hi> 'tis <hi>Topic</hi> and <hi>Endemial</hi> engender'd by bad diet, bad water and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholeſom Air, as the <hi>Leproſy</hi> in <hi>Egypt, Great Spleens</hi> and the <hi>Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy</hi> in <hi>Holland.</hi> This Opinion of all others ſeems trueſt, as I have fully demonſtrated in my <hi>Treatiſe of the Pox.</hi> The firſt Opinion is already confuted, the Second is alſo falſe: for the <hi>Pox</hi> is not a <hi>New</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary</hi> Diſeaſe ſent by Divine Juſtice; for 'twas brought into Chriſtendome from the <hi>Weſt Indies</hi> by <hi>Columbus</hi> and the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and propagated by Contagion and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as is notoriouſly known and atteſted by all. Nor is it now more fierce than 'twas in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but continues ſtill the very ſame. The Ground of this Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take I conceive to be this: Theſe men did not take a full and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46270:11"/>view of the Pox, as 'tis in the ſeveral parts of the World, but only conſider'd it as it now ſhows it ſelf in ſome Northern cold Country. For the Pox does notably differ according to the temper and quality of the Country. In the <hi>Torrid Zone</hi> 'tis mild and gentle, ſo alſo in <hi>Barbary, Egypt,</hi> and among the <hi>Aſiatique Turks</hi> 'tis not outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious. But in <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> 'tis more cruel. So the farther North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward you go, the more fierce you'l find it: for in <hi>Germany, Holland</hi> and <hi>Great-Britain</hi> it handles the Patient more roughly than in <hi>Italy, Spain</hi> or <hi>France.</hi> And the <hi>Danes,</hi> the <hi>Swedes</hi> and the <hi>Ruſſians</hi> will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form you that it deals more rudely with them than with <hi>us</hi> or the <hi>Hollander.</hi> The Diſeaſe in it ſelf without doubt is juſt as it was in the beginnnig, but if the <hi>Hollander</hi> finds his <hi>Pox</hi> not accompanied with ſuch mild Symptoms as the <hi>Spaniſh</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:46270:12"/>or <hi>Italian Phyſicians</hi> mention, let him not think there's any Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made in the Diſeaſe; but let him impute it wholly to the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Climates, and to the cold, foggy Air of that humid Region. In like manner thoſe who embrace the firſt opinion, <hi>viz.</hi> that it does decline and abate of its former fury, ought to conſider, that now Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians have found out an Expedite Way to cure it, and abate its Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms; but at firſt they had no <hi>certain Remedies,</hi> but let it run on to its height. And, beſides, the <hi>French Army</hi> before <hi>Naples</hi> feeding upon unwholeſome diet, the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction met with Bodies full of ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and ſtrangely diſorder'd: All which might encreaſe the Diſeaſe, and raiſe its malignity to an higher degree in that Army at that time, than 'twas in other places where their Bodies were not ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd. So that ſtill the Diſeaſe is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46270:12"/>the ſame, and as furious as ever: but now 'tis checkt and kept under, and formerly 'twas not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The Author commiſerates the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Incontinent Perſons, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves to help them to the utmoſt. He declares his modeſt Intentions, his Charity, and the Cauſes of publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing this Treatiſe.</head>
               <p>THE very name <hi>POX,</hi> ſounds terrible to Engliſh Ears, and makes an Impreſſion of Horrour upon us. For this aggregative Evil is like <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>'s Box, out of which all other Diſeaſes and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs iſſue. When a man is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taqu'd with the Pox, he has not one ſingle Diſeaſe alone, but a Legion of Maladies preſently after ſeize his miſerable Body; <hi>viz. Gonorrhoeas,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46270:13"/>Buboes, Chancres, Caruncles, Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guries, ſtoppages of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine, Chironi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> and <hi>Telephian <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers, Fiſtulas, ill-natur'd Scabs, Tetters, Eroſion</hi> and <hi>Rottenneſs of Bones, Loſs of hair, Falling of Noſes, conſuming of the Palat of the Mouth, Loſs of Speech, Deafneſs, Blindneſs, terrible racking Night-pains, Invincible Head-ach, loſs of Sculls, Falling-ſickneſſes, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions, Apoplexies, dangerous Catarrhs</hi> and <hi>Defluxions of Rheum,</hi> whence enſue <hi>perillous Aſthmas, ſpitting of Bloud, Conſumptions. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctick Feavers, wonderful Extenua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Body, Gummoſities, Nodes,</hi> and <hi>Tophaceous Excreſcencies.</hi> Theſe, and an hundred more are the dire Companions of the Pox. And who can but wonder, that miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man ſhould be ſo deſperately hardy, and ſo <hi>abſorpt</hi> in <hi>Senſuality,</hi> as for one moment of <hi>vaniſhing pleaſure,</hi> to involve himſelf in ſuch an Abyſs of <hi>laſting Miſeries?</hi> But,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46270:13"/>when I conſider the Imperious and <hi>charming Power</hi> of a <hi>Good Face,</hi> the <hi>bewitching Artifices</hi> of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Man's <hi>natural Propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> to <hi>Venus,</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <hi>rapid violence</hi> of his Paſſion, it draws me from <hi>Admiration</hi> to <hi>Commiſerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> For we are all <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſubject to the ſame Paſſions, to the ſame Propenſions and Inclinations of Nature. That man ſaid excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent well in the Comedy, <hi>Homo ſum, humani à me nihil alienum puto.</hi> For though ſome have that Fortitude not to be hurri'd along with this brutiſh Paſſion; yet are they not to inſult over others, who have more of <hi>Paſſion,</hi> and leſs of <hi>Prudence</hi> than themſelves. For Greenneſs of years, and Vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Temptation, though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God they avail the Delinquent nothing at all; yet ought they to merit Compaſſion from us, who have been our ſelves too often aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46270:14"/>by theſe impetuous Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>tumultuantis Nature.</hi> It was therefore <hi>Commiſeration</hi> that caus'd me to ſpend ſo many good hours and years in ſtudying to holp theſe miſerable Perſons. Formerly I did believe that all thoſe, who had once felt the <hi>fury</hi> of <hi>this Diſeaſe,</hi> would afterwards be more wary; but I was deceiv'd, and my conſtant Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations have now ſatisfied me to the contrary. For many do ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge this brutiſh Paſſion, that as ſoon as they are out of the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian's <hi>Hands,</hi> they run preſently into the <hi>Arms</hi> and <hi>Embraces</hi> of infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Courtizans. Nay, too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently we find, that whilſt they are under Cure, they ſecretly conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue the ſame Courſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deum conteſtor,</hi> I call the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and Immortal God to witneſs, whem I dore and ſerve, and who is conſcious to all my Thoughts and Secrets, that I have not publiſh'd
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:46270:14"/>this Treatiſe with any deſign or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to indulge or countenance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continent perſons in their Luſts and deteſtable Lives; but merely for the <hi>Good</hi> of their Perſons, for the <hi>Safety</hi> and <hi>Security</hi> of the <hi>Sober part</hi> of Mankind, and for the <hi>Honour</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. I have publiſh'd this <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Method</hi> for the <hi>Good</hi> of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banchée</hi> himſelf. His Vices &amp; his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continency I hate, but his Perſon I pity and love. Nor can this <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient</hi> juſtly be thought any En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to him, to go on in his Debauchery; for we ſee with our eyes, that notwithſtanding the <hi>Pox</hi> is ſuch a fierce and formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Evil, and the very <hi>Endemial</hi> and <hi>Topique</hi> diſeaſe of <hi>Bawdy-Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> yet the <hi>Greatneſs</hi> of the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and the <hi>Commonneſs</hi> of the Diſeaſe do not at all deter men from ſuch Courſes and Company, but ſtill they ruſh into moſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46270:15"/>danger, brutiſhly preferring one hours Contentment before Health, Life and Heaven it ſelf. Moreover, if we reflect upon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ages (before <hi>Columbus's</hi> Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages to the <hi>Indies</hi>) when this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe was unknown to theſe parts of the world, we ſhall find that men were then far more continent than now; then Debauchery was not at ſuch height. But ſince the <hi>Pox</hi> has invaded <hi>Europe,</hi> and attaqu'd <hi>Bawdy-Houſes,</hi> and been the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Companion of Courtizans, they are wonderfully increas'd, and far more frequented than formerly; <hi>Nitimur in vetitum.</hi> The more we are reſtrain'd, the more impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly we ruſh on. This <hi>Hurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane</hi> by its rapid violence, drives miſerable Mortals into theſe <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nices &amp; Cryptae,</hi> where they are ſure to be ſtung by theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e. Courtizans</hi> ten times more ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous than the Serpents of <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia.</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:46270:15"/>What ſhall we do in this caſe? you'l ſay, <hi>Let 'em go on and periſh in their wickedneſs.</hi> This is indeed a moſt compendious way of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Mankind, <hi>to cut off the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> But we find not that God, or any good Prince ever made uſe of this <hi>rough way. Apage Carnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces!</hi> Away with theſe uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Perſons! and let us diſcharge our Duty, and endeavour to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their <hi>Bodies</hi> from the Fury of this <hi>Peſt,</hi> leaving their <hi>better part</hi> to the Care and Prudence of <hi>Good Divines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. This Treatiſe is deſign'd for the <hi>Safety</hi> and <hi>Security</hi> of the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Part</hi> of Mankind. How many <hi>chaſt Matrous, tender Infants, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Nurſes,</hi> are ruin'd by this <hi>Diſeaſe?</hi> When I ſadly reflect upon the <hi>miſerable Condition</hi> of ſome <hi>virtuous Women:</hi> how <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly debauch'd</hi> ſome Husbands are: and, how frequently the <hi>Pox</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:46270:16"/>is made uſe of as a <hi>ready Expedient</hi> to diſpatch <hi>Wives,</hi> and ſend 'em to another World; I lament the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery</hi> of thoſe Women, and deteſt the <hi>execrable Villany</hi> of thoſe Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands. It is therefore for the <hi>Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zy</hi> of theſe <hi>ſober Perſons,</hi> and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent thoſe <hi>Helliſh Practices</hi> that I have ſet forth this <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Theſe innocent Matrons, conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing only with ſober company, are utterly unacquainted with the Signs and Symptoms of the <hi>Pox.</hi> Hence when unkind Husbands give them the <hi>Running of the Reins,</hi> they innocently believe it nothing but the <hi>Whites,</hi> and ſo let the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe run on. So alſo they imagine thoſe <hi>racking Night-pains</hi> of the <hi>Pox,</hi> to be the Effects of the <hi>Scurvy</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (ſo apt is this Nation and Age to reduce all Diſeaſes to the <hi>Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy.</hi>) This Ignorance of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, as alſo the <hi>ingenit</hi> and <hi>natural Modeſty</hi> of that Sex, are too often
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:46270:16"/>the Cauſes why the buſineſs is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd, and the Diſeaſe conceal'd, untill 'tis ſo rooted in the Body beyond a poſſibility of Cure. And ſo theſe <hi>miſerable</hi> perſons are hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri'd out or this World by a filthy Diſeaſe. I dare confidently avouch it, that one half of <hi>Infected Perſints</hi> are <hi>Innoce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> and further; that where <hi>one</hi> debauch'd perſon dies of the <hi>Pox, five</hi> of the <hi>ſober part</hi> of Mankind die of the ſome Diſeaſe: &amp; the Reaſon is, becauſe the <hi>Deban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chéé</hi> is confident, and diſcovers his Diſeaſe, and in time gets help. But the other not being skill'd in the buſineſs, let it run to its height, before they underſtand what it is: and when they do underſtand it, ſuch is their invincible <hi>Shamefae' d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> that they chooſe rather to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure its utmoſt Fury, than to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover themſelves attainted with ſo ſcandalous a Malady. Add alſo thoſe <hi>miſerable Infants,</hi> who bring
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46270:17"/>a <hi>Congenit</hi> or <hi>Connatural Pox</hi> into the World with them; and alſo thoſe <hi>Innocent Babes</hi> who get it from wicked Nurſes, whoſe Cryes, Tears, and piteous Moans, deſerve ſome regard. All which, I ſay, being duely conſider'd, are enough to move any heart (unleſs flinty) to commiſeration and pity. This Treatiſe therefore is chiefly deſign'd for the benefit of <hi>ſober Mankind,</hi> viz. <hi>chaſt Matrons, tender Infants,</hi> and <hi>innocent Nurſes,</hi> and not for <hi>Bawds</hi> and <hi>Courtizans.</hi> For I heartily wiſh ſuch damn'd Proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, who make Leachery a Trade, may either periſh of the Pox, or be ſo <hi>juſt</hi> to themſelves, and <hi>kind</hi> to Mankind, to end their curſed lives with an <hi>Halter.</hi> The <hi>End</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and <hi>Scope</hi> of this preſent Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, is, not to remove the Pox from <hi>Bawdy-houſes</hi> and <hi>Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizans,</hi> but from <hi>Marriage-beds</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:46270:17"/>and <hi>Cradies,</hi> from <hi>innocent</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerving Perſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. I have publiſh'd this <hi>Defenſive Method</hi> for the <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Hontour</hi> of this <hi>Nation.</hi> The Pox is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to Mankind it ſelf, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected Perſons may juſtly be rank'd among the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous Animals.</hi> For, what Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents in: the Deſarts of <hi>Africa</hi> ejacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late more filthy Venom than <hi>Pocky Men</hi> and <hi>Women?</hi> This dire Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom of the <hi>Pox</hi> tranſcends that of <hi>Vipers</hi> and <hi>Adders,</hi> and is far more extenſive of its malice. <hi>That</hi> kills Creatures of a different kind only, <hi>this</hi> poyſons thoſe of its own <hi>ſpecies;</hi> and when Men and Women by the Impulſe of <hi>Venus</hi> come together, they poyſon one another. In ſome hot Countries, almoſt the moyety of Mankind is infected with this diſgraceful <hi>Malady.</hi> And who can but be mightily concern'd to ſee one half of Mankind come in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:46270:18"/>the number of <hi>pernicious Animals,</hi> and <hi>Creatures that ejaculate poyſon?</hi> If you enter into a <hi>ſerious</hi> (I am ſure 'twill be a <hi>ſad</hi>) Conſideration, and attentively remarque what footing the <hi>French Pox</hi> has got up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Engliſh Ground:</hi> what huge Multitudes of <hi>Pocky Patients</hi> come every year under <hi>Healing Hands;</hi> you'l quickly grant that this <hi>Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient</hi> is <hi>very ſeaſonable,</hi> and that there's an <hi>abſolute Neceſſity</hi> of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing ſome <hi>Defenſives</hi> to repreſs the <hi>Fury</hi> and <hi>farther ſpreading</hi> of this <hi>diffuſive Evil.</hi> A multitude of Lawyers is an Argument of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Law-ſuits.</hi> And if we argue from this <hi>Topic,</hi> we may eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the <hi>Pox</hi> to be prodigiouſly ſpread in this City. For, ſetting <hi>learned Phyſicians</hi> aſide; you'l find an incredible multitude of Perſons who live (and ſome very ſplendid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly too) chiefly upon the <hi>Cure</hi> of <hi>this Diſeaſe.</hi> The numerous mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:46270:18"/>of <hi>Surgeons, Chymiſts, Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing Apothecaries, Mountebancks, Empiriques, Tooth-drawers</hi> and <hi>Ignoramuſſes</hi> who deal in the <hi>Pox,</hi> upon a ſober Inquiry have been found to amount to near <hi>one thouſand</hi> and <hi>five hundred.</hi> And if ſo many Perſons live upon the Pox, judge how many thouſands ſuffer by the contagion of that <hi>ſpreading Diſeaſe.</hi> It will therefore be a <hi>generous</hi> and <hi>Heroio <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> to endeavour by ſome <hi>bealing Advice</hi> to help this Nation, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs and check the enormous ſpreading of this <hi>popular Diſtemper.</hi> And that perſon who ſhall well perform it, will truely merit to be eſteem'd, a <hi>Benefactor</hi> to Mankind. I have broken the Ice, and made a good <hi>Ouverture,</hi> let others follow my Example, <hi>facile eſt inventis ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:46270:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> A Search into the Cauſes, why Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians bitherto have not endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Prevention and Extinction of the Pox. Three Reaſons aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd, <hi>viz.</hi> Pride, Covetouſneſs, and Ignorance. The Author re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrates the great Inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Hazards he voluntarily thruſts himſelf upon for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Good, and for the Honour and Safety of the Engliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
               <p>IT's now almoſt two Hundred years, ſince the <hi>French Army</hi> at <hi>Naples</hi> was firſt infected with the Pox. I cannot but greatly admire that all the Phyſitians in the world have ſate ſtill; and let it run on thus long, and done nothing in the <hi>Defenſive Way,</hi> towards its Preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:46270:19"/>or Extinction. They have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed writ whole Volums and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes how to cure it, but they have not ſet forth in Vulgar Languages any <hi>Defenſive Methods</hi> to prevent the Infection or farther ſpreading of that <hi>abominable Diſeaſe.</hi> They have not propos'd any <hi>Expedient</hi> to root it out from the <hi>Européan</hi> part of Mankind. Certainly it is a far more excellent piece of skill, to preſerve Mankind from Diſeaſes, than to cure him when infected. And ſurely all Chriſtian Phyſicians ought to have joyn'd their Forces, and bent their, beſt Endeavours to have quell'd ſo formidable and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious an Enemy, and, which ſo inſolently menaces Mankind with Ruine and Deſtruction. But, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not one word of this. None have yet inſtructed Mankind in this <hi>weighty Affair.</hi> There is, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, a matter of a dozen among the many Authours who have
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:46270:20"/>writ of this Diſeaſe, that have laid down <hi>Defenſive Methods</hi> againſt the Pox; but their Diſcourſes are in Latin, and add reſt to Phyſicians onely, ſo that the generality can receive no benefit by them, unleſs tranſlated and adapted to their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities. But what is the Cauſe of this Silence in a matter of ſuch <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Concern?</hi> I have made ſearch into the Buſineſs, and I find the Reaſons chiefly to be theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Moſt of the Eminent Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians of this City and Nation have always look'd upon this Difeaſe as a thing below them; and ſo not at all concern'd themſelves either with its <hi>Cure</hi> or <hi>Prevention,</hi> but wholly remitted the buſineſs to others of an <hi>inferior Claſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe others who have ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died the Diſeaſe, have been ſo great Gainers by it, that in ſtead of endeavouring its <hi>Prevention</hi> or <hi>Extinction,</hi> they have with'd its
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:46270:20"/>
                  <hi>increaſe</hi> and <hi>farther Propagation'</hi> ſo greedy is Mankind of Profit! Theſe men have carri'd it fair to the World, and craftily difguiz'd their Avarice with the ſpecious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> alledging that the Diſcovery of <hi>ways</hi> of <hi>Preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> might be an <hi>Incentive</hi> to Luſt. Whereas they have been Eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the contrary, and have daily ſeen, that the <hi>Greatneſs</hi> of the <hi>Dunger,</hi> and <hi>Commonneſs</hi> of the <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> have not at all deterr'd men, or kept them within the Bounds of Continency.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Illiterate Surgeons, Empiriques,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mountebanks,</hi> who pretend to this Cure, being perſons ignorant in the very Rudiments of <hi>Phyſick,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the thing to be impoſtible; and ſo never attempt any thing in the <hi>Prophylactique Way.</hi> Theſe <hi>poor Hearts</hi> conſult <hi>Vulcan</hi> more than <hi>Apollo;</hi> they ſpend their time in <hi>Laboratories</hi> among Furnaces
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:46270:21"/>and Crucibles, where they pite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly torture themſelves, and the poor Minerals, to extort and draw forth <hi>Elixirs, Quinteſſences, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> &amp;c. and vainly promiſe to themſelves and others the effecting of Wonders. But they are ſo far from performing any ſolid Cure, and eſpecially in the Pox, that they either murther the poor Patient with their malignant Medicines of <hi>Antimony</hi> and <hi>Quick-ſilver;</hi> or ſo affix the diſeaſe to him, that 'tis af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards impoſſible to be remov'd. That was a notable Saying of a Gentleman, who had been guilty of this Imprudence, in addreſſing to <hi>Illiterate Surgeons</hi> for help in this Caſe: <hi>I carried,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>a Clap to the Surgeon, and he gave me the Box for it.</hi> For theſe men have an <hi>Excellent Faculty</hi> that way; for in driving in <hi>Buboes,</hi> and unwary ſuppreſſing <hi>Gonorrhoeas,</hi> they uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bring a <hi>ſlight ſuperficiary Clap</hi> to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:46270:21"/>a <hi>Grand Pox.</hi> And when they meet with a <hi>Confirm'd Pox,</hi> by their <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Medicines</hi> and <hi>prepoſterous handling</hi> the Patient, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly exaſperate the <hi>Malady,</hi> wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the ſick perſon, and in the end make his Diſeaſe deſperate and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable.</p>
               <p>Theſe therefore I conceive to be the Cauſes, why none have ſtood up to vindicate Mankind from this <hi>reproachful Diſeaſe;</hi> why none have made it their buſineſs to endeavour the <hi>Prevention</hi> and <hi>Extinction</hi> of this <hi>pernicious Evil.</hi> The Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of <hi>prime Note</hi> have been too fine-finger'd to meddle with this <hi>foul Diſeaſe.</hi> The others who have ſtudied the Caſe, have forborn to ſet forth any <hi>Prophylactique Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod,</hi> becauſe they have not ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Publique Good,</hi> but their own <hi>private Intereſt.</hi> And laſtly, the <hi>rabble</hi> of <hi>ignorant Surgeons, Empiriques,</hi> and <hi>Mountebanks,</hi> have not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:46270:22"/>help't Mankind in this important Affair, becauſe the Enterpriſe is too heavy for their weak ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
               <p>I alone am the Singular Perſon that ſtand up, to <hi>help</hi> the <hi>unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Debauchée,</hi> to <hi>defend</hi> and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure</hi> the <hi>Sober part</hi> of Mankind, <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Matrons, Innocent Nurſes,</hi> and <hi>tender Infants</hi> from the fury of the <hi>Pox;</hi> to <hi>vindicate</hi> the Honour of this Nation, and draw a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable part thereof from among the <hi>venemons</hi> and <hi>pernicious Beaſts.</hi> Neither am I ignorant of the grand Inconveniencies and dangers which by this <hi>Charitable Deſign</hi> I ſhall voluntarily draw upon my own head. For</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some peeviſh and reſtleſs Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits will open their venemous mouths, and endeavour to miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the Cauſes and Ends of this preſent Undertaking.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In diſcovering this <hi>Prophyla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctique
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:46270:22"/>Method,</hi> I ſhall draw upon my ſelf the Envy of ſome <hi>Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> the high diſpleaſure of <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous,</hi> and the Hatred of <hi>Emperiques,</hi> and <hi>Mountebanks.</hi> And indeed not without ſome Cauſe: for in taking the Pox away from this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I ſhall rob theſe men of the beſt Flower in their Garden. <hi>Hine ille lachrymae!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſetting forth this <hi>Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> to <hi>root out</hi> the <hi>Pox,</hi> is ſuch a ſtrange piece of <hi>Sulf-denyal,</hi> and ſo infinitely repugnant to my own <hi>Profit</hi> and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> that many will condemn me for it, as much want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my own Good. For, I, who for almoſt this twenty years, have had conſiderable Practice in the Cure of this Diſeaſe, now to iſſue out a Treatiſe to <hi>prevent</hi> and <hi>root out the Pox,</hi> what is it but to lay the Ax to the root of the Tree, and cut off all hopes of any <hi>further Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit?</hi> It is ſo, I confeſs: but here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:46270:23"/>I have had regard only to the <hi>publique Good,</hi> to the <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>fifety of Mankind,</hi> and not at all to my own <hi>Intereſt.</hi> Gentlemen, I have ever look'd upon the Practice of Phyſick, not as a <hi>Sordid,</hi> but <hi>Sacred</hi> thing; and have always hated thoſe baſe Spirits, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the heaping up of Riches, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the welfare of <hi>Mankind.</hi> Thoſe <hi>pedantique Reſervs</hi> and <hi>Conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of Knowledge become <hi>Empi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riques</hi> and not <hi>rational Phyſicians,</hi> who ought generouſly to mind the <hi>publique Concern</hi> of a Nation, and not their <hi>own Intereſt</hi> only.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> theſe are the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences I ſhall voluntarily draw upon my own head, by my charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſign to contribute to the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Good,</hi> and to help you in this <hi>Affair.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:46270:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> The Author demonſtrates the Poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Facility of his Defenſive Method from Reaſon and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and alſo from the Practice, Authority and Teſtimonies of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe great and renown'd Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe for almoſt 200 years the World has ſate ſtill, and not attempted any thing in the <hi>Prophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lactique Way,</hi> nor any ways en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to root out the Pox; the greateſt part of Mankind have therefore concluded the thing <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible,</hi> and do now crroneouſly believe that the Pox cannot be prevented by any Art whatſoever. But, for the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Safety</hi> of Mankind, I ſhall in this preſont Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe undeceive theſe misbelieving
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:46270:24"/>perſons, and fully demonſtrate from Reaſon and Experience, and alſo from the Practice, Authority and Teſtimonies of ſome great Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that <hi>'tis poſſible to prevent the Pox,</hi> and that this way <hi>of Prevention is Eaſie, Effectual, and Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I prove the Poſſibility of this <hi>Defenſive Method</hi> thus. All Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in treating of the <hi>Prophylactique way</hi> to ſecure the Body from <hi>Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and cure <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the dangerous <hi>Bites</hi> and <hi>Wounds</hi> of <hi>Serpents</hi> and other <hi>venemous Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals,</hi> commonly propoſe two things, 1. To fortifie the whole body, or that part onely which is moſt obnoxious to danger, and make it impaſſible. Or, 2. by <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pique Remedies</hi> to draw forth the Venom, before it has made any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable impreſſion upon the body. Now Reaſon and Experience tell us, that this is to be perform'd
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:46270:24"/>in the venemous Bites, Wounds, and Impreſſes of the greateſt and fierceſt of Poyſons. For example, the <hi>Bite</hi> of a <hi>mad Dog</hi> is eaſily ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the great impendent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of <hi>Hydrophobia</hi> moſt certainly prevented. The Bite alſo and Wound of the <hi>Viper, Aſp, Seps, Dryinus,</hi> &amp;c. may, and have fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently been cur'd, and all danger prevented by <hi>Topique,</hi> and <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Remedies.</hi> Hence then I ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue; If the fierce venom of theſe Beaſts (ſome whereof kill in few hours) may be prevented by <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Theriacal Medicines</hi> fortifying Nature, and thruſting forth the Poyſon, and alſo by apt <hi>Topique Applications,</hi> drawing the Venom from the part affected: then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the Pox alſo may be preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Proper Remedies</hi> and <hi>Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations.</hi> For, 1. the above mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Poyſons are far more fierce and quick in operation than that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:46270:25"/>the <hi>Pox.</hi> And 2. they bring more dangerous Symptoms, becauſe they direct their malice chiefly againſt the Heart, and ſo quickly deſtroy the whole Oeconomy of Nature. But the Venom of the Pox is more dull and ſluggiſh, and at firſt ſeizes the <hi>Glans</hi> onely, and continues there ſome hours, before it makes any farther Progreſs, or diffuſes its malignity to any other part. 3. Why may not the Pox be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, or remov'd when 'tis ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficiary, and in the Genital parts onely? For the Remedies preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in the following Chapters, are the very ſame that are us'd to an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Pox,</hi> when t'is fix'd and rooted in the body, and certainly any Rational man will grant, that thoſe Remedies which are able to overcome an <hi>old confirm'd Pox,</hi> where the Venom has taken deep rooting in the body, and is as it were naturaliz'd; the ſame may
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:46270:25"/>alſo with greater facility remove a <hi>ſuperficiary Impreſs</hi> of Venom and Malignity. The Decoction of <hi>Guaiacum</hi> is a known <hi>Antidote</hi> againſt the <hi>Pox;</hi> ſo alſo is a <hi>Suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>Cinnabaris.</hi> And if <hi>Guaia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oum, Cinnabaris,</hi> &amp;c. can cure an <hi>Inveterate Pox,</hi> who can deny that the firſt Rudiments and <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mordia</hi> of the Pox may be remov'd by the ſame?</p>
               <p>Let then theſe Sophiſters, who envy Man's <hi>Honour, Safety</hi> and <hi>Security,</hi> either give us ſome ſolid and ſatisfactory Reaſon, why this <hi>Venom</hi> of the <hi>Pox,</hi> when 'tis ſeated in the outward parts onely, may not be expell'd by <hi>internal Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes,</hi> and drawn forth by <hi>Topique Applications,</hi> as well as other Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which are of a far more fierce and malignant nature. Or, in caſe they cannot give any ſuch Reaſon as I am ſure they cannot) then let 'em yield up the Cauſe, and confeſs
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:46270:26"/>the <hi>Poſſibility</hi> of this <hi>Defenſive Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that this <hi>Defenſive Method</hi> may be more fully confirm'd and eſtabliſh'd, I ſhall in the next place ſhew, that it has been alſo the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timent of ſeveral learned Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of <hi>this</hi> and the <hi>laſt</hi> Ages; who have in Latin publiſh'd <hi>Defenſives,</hi> and ſhew'd how to <hi>prevent the Pox.</hi> 1. <hi>Gabriel Falloppius,</hi> that learned Phyſician, in his Book <hi>de Morbo Gall. cap.</hi> 89. ſets down at large how to <hi>prevent</hi> the <hi>Pox,</hi> and atteſts upon Oath the <hi>Certainty</hi> and <hi>Infallibility</hi> of his <hi>Defenſive Preſcription.</hi> 2. <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtachius Rudius de morbis occultis &amp; venen. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap</hi> 13. has excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently perform'd the ſame Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking. 3. <hi>Hercules Saxonia</hi> has done the like in his Treatiſe <hi>de Lue Venerea, cap.</hi> 16. 4. <hi>Roderi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus à Fonſeca, Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>Conſultat.</hi> 35. out of <hi>Falloppius</hi> and <hi>Petroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> has diſcuſs'd the Queſtion, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:46270:26"/>ſeems propenſe to the <hi>Affirmative.</hi> 5. <hi>Julius Palmarius de Lue ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 8. believ'd alſo that it was <hi>poſſible</hi> to fortify the body, and <hi>prevent</hi> the <hi>Pox.</hi> 6. <hi>Joannes Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randaeus</hi> was of the ſame mind al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, as is manifeſt from the method he ſets down in 's Book <hi>de Lue Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerea,</hi> and from thoſe words, <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt eos qui de Lue Venerea ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctenus ſcripſerunt, nihil de Prophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxi ejus attigiſſe, ſed omnes ſoli Therapiae incumbere.</hi> 7. <hi>Panarolus,</hi> a Roman Phyſician in 's book of <hi>Obſervations,</hi> has ſet down a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylacticon,</hi> to preſerve Women from the Pox. Theſe are all Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians of <hi>prime Note,</hi> and they did firmly believe the <hi>Poſsibility of the</hi> Thing, and have ſet forth <hi>Ways</hi> of <hi>Prevention.</hi> But in this one thing they fail'd, and were wanting to the <hi>Publique Good,</hi> viz. they did not publiſh their <hi>Defenſives</hi> in Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Languages, (as I have done) but
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:46270:27"/>addreſs'd their Diſcourſes to Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians only. But in the enſuing Chapters I ſhall teach them to ſpeak Engliſh, and, to their utmoſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct you in this. <hi>Important Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Some Practique Obſervations concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the manner of receiving In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. What Perſons are moſt apt to give and receive the Pox. The Author propoſes his Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and Defenſives; and ſhen's how to prevent the Pox by Bandage and Ligature, by Lotions, Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Suffiments.</head>
               <p>HAving in the precedent Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters declar'd the Cauſes and Reaſons of this Undertaking, and demonſtrated the <hi>Poſſibility</hi> of the thing; and alſo made a Search into
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:46270:27"/>the Cauſes why Phyſicians hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to have not endeavour'd to <hi>root out</hi> this <hi>filthy Diſeaſe:</hi> I come now to the <hi>Grand Buſineſs,</hi> to diſcover this <hi>Prophylactique,</hi> and lay down this <hi>Expedient</hi> to <hi>root out</hi> the <hi>Pox.</hi> This <hi>Expedient</hi> conſiſts of two things, the <hi>firſt</hi> whereof is, a laying down ſome <hi>Defenſive Remedies</hi> to ſecure particular perſons from receiving <hi>Infection</hi> from <hi>Pockie Women.</hi> The <hi>ſecond</hi> is a <hi>Secluſion</hi> of infected Courtizans from Publique Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, but yet ſo as this <hi>Secluſion</hi> may be commodious to this Nation, and alſo a deſign of <hi>Charity</hi> to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes</hi> themſelves. We ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of this <hi>Secluſion</hi> towards the end of this Treatiſe. But in the firſt place we will enquire after the <hi>Defenſives,</hi> and lay them down in a plain, familiar, and intelligible Method; and alſo call in a dozen of the learnedſt Phyſicians in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom, to give their Sentiments
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:46270:28"/>in the Caſe; whoſe <hi>Judgments</hi> and <hi>Preſcriptions</hi> will farther explicate, confirm, and enlarge the whole bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs.</p>
               <p>But firſt we are to conſider three things: Firſt, what kind of <hi>Pocky Women</hi> are moſt dangerous and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious, and when? Secondly, what men are moſt apt to receive Infection? and Thirdly, the Way or Manner how the Pox is imparted to the body.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What kind of <hi>Pockie Women</hi> are moſt dangerous? I anſwer, that young Women are more infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious than Ancient: ſo alſo thoſe who are of a ſpare, thin, cholerique Conſtitution of body, and alſo ſuch as are of a ſanguin, hot, and moiſt complexion; and laſtly, thoſe who have the Pox complicate with the <hi>Scurvy.</hi> The Reaſon is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt: for young women are more hot and moiſt than old, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, the Venom in ſuch bodies
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:46270:28"/>muſt needs be more diffuſive of it ſelf, than 'tis in an old, dry, and cold body. The Pox is very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant in a cholerique, hot, and dry Conſtitution; becauſe by the great heat of the Body the Venom is calcin'd and advanc'd to a high degree of Malignity. In bodies which are ſanguin, hot and moiſt, the Venom is active, ſpirituous, and quick, becauſe <hi>Heat</hi> and <hi>Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture</hi> increaſe Putrefaction and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of Humours; and being <hi>diffuſive qualities,</hi> ſoon communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and ſpread the Venom. And laſtly, the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> in the judgment of all who have writ of it, is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous contagious Diſeaſe, and ſomething of kin to the Pox; ſo according to the Proverb, <hi>Vis uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta fortion,</hi> a combination of Venoms is moſt forcible. But of all Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſhe who is dull, ſluggiſh, and of a phlegmatique, groſs, cold Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution is the leaſt infectious: for
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:46270:29"/>ſuch a woman, if ſhe have no <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norrhoea,</hi> nor <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers</hi> in the <hi>uterin Paſſage,</hi> does not very quickly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate the Pox, but many times the firſt that converſes with her, receives no dammage at all; but the ſecond, who comes upon her when her body is heated, and the Venom agitated and ſtirr'd, receives the Pox. A <hi>Gonorrhoea</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers</hi> in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>terin Paſſage</hi> may be gueſs'd at by the Lubricity and Moiſture of thoſe parts.</p>
               <p>The other part of the Queſtion is, When are <hi>Pockie Women</hi> moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious? <hi>Anſw.</hi> When the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom and Humours are moſt agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and heated with <hi>Wine, Hearing Drinks,</hi> and <hi>burning Luſt.</hi> For all theſe things heat the body, agitate the infectious Humours, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the Venom. But above all the moſt dangerous time to meddle with ſuch women, is, when they have their <hi>Courſes.</hi> For at that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:46270:29"/>time Nature mightily endeavours to diſcharge all the Venom and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purities of the whole Body that way, ſo that of neceſſity they muſt be exceeding pernicious at ſuch times.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond Thing to be conſider'd, is, what men are moſt apt to receive Infection? I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Young people receive it far ſooner than Ancient, ſo alſo thoſe who are of a ſanguin, hot, and moiſt conſtitution of body, but eſpecially when they are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> under the greateſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and moſt <hi>rapid Commotion</hi> of <hi>Luſt.</hi> And laſtly, thoſe who have the <hi>Glans</hi> cover'd with the <hi>Praepuce.</hi> Now that this is ſo, is manifeſt from Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation: and it's alſo atteſted and confirmed by that learned Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>Gabriel Falloppius,</hi> in's Book <hi>dè morbo Gallico,</hi> cap. 22. who gives this Reaſon of it, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Glans,</hi> by reaſon 'tis conſtantly cover'd with
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:46270:30"/>the <hi>Praepuce,</hi> is moſt tender, ſoft, and ſuſceptive of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <hi>venemous Impreſſes</hi> of the <hi>Pox:</hi> but on the contrary, when that part is bare and unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd, it becomes more firm, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact and hardned, and does not ſo eaſily admit the Venom. <hi>Hercules Saxonia; dè Lue Venerea, cap.</hi> 4. grants the thing to be true, but he thinks <hi>Falloppius</hi> miſtaken in the cauſe: for he is of opinion, that 'tis not becauſe the part is more ſoft and tender, but becauſe the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom does inſinuate between the <hi>Glans</hi> and <hi>Praepuce,</hi> and afterwards impart its malignity to the whole body. For my part, I believe theſe learned men are both in the right: for without doubt, as <hi>Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lappius</hi> aſſerts, when the <hi>Glans</hi> is perpetually cover'd, the skin muſt of neceſſity be more looſe, thin and warm, and much eaſier admit the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:46270:30"/>Venom than when 'tis otherwiſe. So alſo, according to <hi>Saxonia,</hi> the Venom does inſinuate between the <hi>Glans</hi> and <hi>Praepuce,</hi> and more cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attaque the Patient. But of this we have diſcours'd more largely in our Treatiſe of the Pox.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Way</hi> or <hi>Manner</hi> how the <hi>Infection</hi> of the Pox is communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Body, is thus: when a Woman gets the Pox from a Man, the Infection is ſometimes receiv'd from the <hi>Chancres</hi> on the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nital, but moſt commonly from his infectious Sperm. When a Man receives it from a Woman, the Contagion inſinuates into the <hi>Glans</hi> from the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>terin Paſſage,</hi> which commonly is full of <hi>Pockie <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers,</hi> or beſmer'd with the virulent matter of a <hi>Gonorrhoea.</hi> Theſe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers</hi> emit a venemous <hi>ſani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,</hi> which infects that tender part call'd the <hi>glans.</hi> Theſe impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Venom remain ſome time
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:46270:31"/>upon the <hi>Glans</hi> onely, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards (if let alone) inſinuate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the humours and ſpirits, and ſo infect the whole body. You are alſo to underſtand, that a Woman may in Coition give the Pox to her Gallant, notwithſtanding ſhe has no <hi>Gonorrhoea,</hi> nor <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers</hi> in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>terin Paſſage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This being premis'd, we come now to the <hi>Defenſive Method.</hi> And here it would be vain and fruitleſs to think to ſecure the body by <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Antidotes</hi> only, and wholly neglect <hi>Topique Applications,</hi> ſeeing that the inward parts at firſt are entire and free, and the Venom lies only in the <hi>glans.</hi> We therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this <hi>Defenſive Method</hi> are to propoſe two things. 1. To make the <hi>Genital part</hi> or member <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, firm and as it were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſible. This has been attempted by <hi>Falloppius,</hi> and ſince by others, who to this purpoſe preſcribe <hi>Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptic
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:46270:31"/>Lotions,</hi> and <hi>Linnen Raggs</hi> impregnated with ſuch decoctions, and apply them to the <hi>Glans</hi> in men, and to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>terin Paſſage</hi> in women, both before and after Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition, as you ſhall ſee in the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chapters. 2. By <hi>Lotions, Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations, Attractives, Suffiments,</hi> &amp;c. to draw forth the Venom whilſt it is in the genital part only, before it get to the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal parts. For this Venom, if com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd with that of other <hi>vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous beaſts,</hi> is ſomewhat dull and ſluggiſh, and for ſome hours moves not, but afterwards (if let alone) it gets into the bloud, and by a continuity of parts ſoon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects the whole body. You are therefore preſently after Coition to make water, for that cleanſes the inward part of the genital. Then uſe <hi>Bandage</hi> or <hi>ſtrict ligature</hi> to that part of the Genital next the belly: for this Ligature compreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:46270:32"/>the Veſſels, and hinders the circulation of the Blood and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and couſequently it hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Venom from inſinuating with the blood into the inward parts. Then foment it with <hi>warm <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine,</hi> or (which is much better) with <hi>white Wine</hi> as hot as can be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dur'd. Waſh all the members, but eſpecially the <hi>Glans.</hi> Do ſo ſeveral times in the day, for two or three days together. Or, this Decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: boyl <hi>Guaiacum, Chamaepitys, Germander, Horehound, Scordium, Aſh-leaves</hi> and <hi>Keyes, Dictamnus Creticus, Gentian,</hi> &amp;c. in white Wine, (if you add a little <hi>Praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitate</hi> 'twill be far more efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) and foment the <hi>Glans</hi> and whole <hi>Part</hi> with it often in a day. After the firſt day, take off the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gature. The Ligature is to be looſen'd when the Patient makes water, or when the Part erects it ſelf and ſwells. After every bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:46270:32"/>apply Pigeons or Whelps new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſſected and hot. Some com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend a Liniment of <hi>Mithridate</hi> or <hi>Venice Treacle.</hi> For theſe things have great virtue to draw forth Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom. You may alſo ſweat four mornings together with an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeme of <hi>Guaiacum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here I conjure and charge all perſons concern'd, not to be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their own good, nor to neglect theſe <hi>Remedies,</hi> or defer the time, but immediately after <hi>Venus</hi> to waſh and mundify the parts with the aforeſaid <hi>Lotions:</hi> and they may be confident of the <hi>Cure.</hi> But if they defer the time, and let the Venom get head, and take rooting in the body, the fault is their own, I have given them fair warning. Note alſo that none is to converſe a whole night with an <hi>infectious woman,</hi> for in twelve hours time the venom may do much hurt, and inſinuate into
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:46270:33"/>the inward parts beyond a poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Extraction by <hi>Topique Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications.</hi> Mundifie therefore the part, and waſh off the <hi>poyſonous</hi> matter with <hi>warm <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine</hi> preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after the Act, then get the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Remedies. <hi>Principiis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta</hi> —</p>
               <p>Sometimes after medling with infected <hi>Women,</hi> the Patient will feel an Itching in the Genital. In this caſe I adviſe you to uſe <hi>Fallop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius's</hi> Suffiment deſcrib'd in the next Chapter, or that of <hi>Varandae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> ſet down in the eleventh Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this Treatiſe. Take a little earthen Pot with ſome live coals in it, and put ſome of the Powder upon the coals, and place an artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Funnel over it, ſo as you may admit the ſmoke to the <hi>glans,</hi> or whole Part: be ſure you do it dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terouſly, that you admit not the cold Air to the part, nor the Smoke to the Patients Noſe or Mouth,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:46270:33"/>and when you have done, wrap it in <hi>warm Cotton.</hi> Do ſo three mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings together. This <hi>Suffiment</hi> is a <hi>potent</hi> Medicine, and to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter'd with diſcretion: put not too much powder upon the coals; neither are you to continue the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration too long. Theſe <hi>Suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> if prudently us'd, are of admirable virtue to <hi>prevent</hi> the <hi>Pox.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What has been already ſaid is ſufficient to prevent the Pox, and ſecure any perſon whatſoever. Yet that our <hi>Defenſive Method</hi> may be compleat and full, I ſhall annex the Preſcriptions of a dozen of the greateſt Phyſicians of this and the laſt Ages.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:46270:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Falloppius his Defenſives to prevent the Pox. Of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Way of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring his Medicinal Linnen. His two Suffiments of excellent virtue in this caſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FAlloppius de Morbo Gallico, cap.</hi> 89. layes down this <hi>Defenſive Method,</hi> to preſerve the body from <hi>Chancres</hi> and the Pox. <hi>Ego nihil fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſe videor,</hi> &amp;c. I might ſeem, <hi>ſays be,</hi> to have done juſt nothing, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs alſo I teach you a way, how, any perſon ſeeing a <hi>beautiful Siren,</hi> and converſing with her, although ſhe be infected, may yet be ſecur'd from the <hi>Pox.</hi> I was always of Opinion, that there was ſome way to be us'd, to prevent <hi>Chancres</hi> and the <hi>Pox.</hi> But what is this way?
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:46270:34"/>I told you formerly, that theſe <hi>Chancres</hi> (or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers</hi> on the <hi>Genital</hi>) were caus'd by little venemous bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, imparted from the infectious woman, and being receiv'd into the poroſities of the <hi>glans,</hi> cauſe an Eruption of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers:</hi> therefore 'tis neceſſary, that after <hi>Venus</hi> we forthwith cleanſe away this vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous matter from the <hi>Glans.</hi> But if it has inſinuated into the Pores, notwithſtanding we waſh the parts with <hi>Wine, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine</hi> or <hi>Water,</hi> yet we cannot waſh off the matter. And this frequently falls out in thoſe, who have the <hi>glans</hi> tender, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd with the <hi>praepuce.</hi> How therefore muſt we proceed? I ever believ'd that we might lay down ſome Remedy, which has power of its own nature to penetrate the skin, and diſperſe the malignant matter, or elſe to draw it forth, or dry it up, and overcome it. Therefore I have invented this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:46270:35"/>Remedy. But becauſe we muſt court theſe Courtizans, and win their Affections, it is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to carry <hi>Oyntments</hi> and <hi>Salves</hi> along with us; therefore I have found out the uſe of a fine lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen Rag, imbu'd and impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a Medicinal virtue, which may conveniently be carri'd with us.— As oft therefore as any ſhall pollute himſelf with theſe Strum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, let him (if poſſibly he can) waſh the Genital part: afterwards let him apply the <hi>Medicinal Rag,</hi> being cut and exactly proportion'd to cover the whole <hi>glans:</hi> let him, I ſay, after coition apply it to the <hi>glans,</hi> and cover it with the <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puce.</hi> If you fear <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers</hi> in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinary paſſage,</hi> put this <hi>Praeſervative Linnen</hi> into that paſſage. <hi>I have experimented this Remedy in a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand; and, I call the Immortal God to witneſs, that not one was infected.</hi> Obſerve alſo that any clean linnen
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:46270:35"/>has a great <hi>preſervative virtue:</hi> alſo new ſoft Cotton, wrapt about the naked <hi>glans,</hi> after you have mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dify'd it with <hi>deterſive Waſhes,</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully preſerves; when the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient takes off this <hi>Lint,</hi> let him look upon it, for he ſhall ſee it ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, and diſcolour'd with a yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowiſh, pale, or blackiſh colour. Let the perſon always wrap this Linnen upon the <hi>Glans</hi> for four or five hours. The way of preparing this <hi>defenſive Linnen</hi> is excellent, and is as follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take Gentian, all three ſorts of Birthwort of each a drachm, white and red Sanders, Wood of Aloes, of each two Scruples; red Coral, Spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium of Ivory, burnt Harts horn, of each half a drachm, Scordium, Sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiſtle, Betony, Seabious, Tormentil, of each one handful; Roſe-leaves a handful and half, Guaiacum two ounces, Squama Aeris two drachms, Praecipitate prepar'd a drachm and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:46270:36"/>of the beſt Muſcadel of Creet one pint and half, waters of Sow-thiſtle and Scabious two pints. Take the Wine and the Water, and infuſe the Guaiacum therein</hi> 24 <hi>hours: then add the other things, and let them boyl 'till half be conſum'd. Then ſtrain forth the Decoction. In this Decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a pure linnen cloth is ſteep'd all night, and afterwards dry'd in the ſhade: this is perform'd three times; for we macerate it thrice, &amp; dry it thrice. After that we cut it inpieces of a juſt proportion to involve the glans, &amp; they are always to be kept in readines.</hi>— The ſame Author gives us another Deſcription of this <hi>Preſervative Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen;</hi> and alſo further proſecutes the buſineſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take round Birthworth, Gentian, white Dittany, of each two drachms, Scordium, Sow-thiſtle, Rue, of each an ounce and half; Wood of Aloes, all three ſorts of Sanders, ſeeds of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, of each a drachm, Rhubarb, Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentil,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:46270:36"/>St. Johns-wort, of each half a drachm, Mithridate two drachms, Guaiacum two: ounces, the beſt Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadel, water of Sow-thiſtle, of each one pint and half. Let the wood be firſt ſteep'd a whole day in the water and wine: afterwards boyl it until the third part be waſted; then put in the other things, and let them be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerated a day; after that boyl them until half be conſum'd: then ſtrain it out. Be careful that the veſſel, wherein your Medicaments boyl, be well clos'd. It would be beſt if it were done in B. M. This being done, take the Linnen, and ſteep it in the Decoction three dayes: then dry it in the ſhade in a hot place; wet it and dry it again: do ſo three times, or oftner, if you pleaſe. This Linnen being well dry'd, keep it for uſe, wrap'd up in paper, or in Linnen.</hi> I might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this Remedy much, but do you try it, your ſelves ſhall be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of its virtue. But, if you are
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:46270:37"/>fearful, and deſire a more potent remedy, and begin to feel an <hi>Itch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in the Genital, go home, and ſuffumigate the <hi>Praepuce</hi> with the enſuing <hi>Suffiment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take am carthen pot, in which put a live coal or two, ſprinkle upon the coals this powder, and by degrees hold the genital part over the Smoke; afterwards take the <hi>prepar'd Linnen</hi> or <hi>clean Cotton</hi> and put it upon the <hi>glans,</hi> and the <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous matter</hi> will be drawn from the Liver. The <hi>Powder</hi> is this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take powder of red Roſes, Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, red Sanders, of each one ſcruple and a half, Benjamin, Camphire, Frankincenſe, Aloes, Myrrh, of each two Scruples, Cinnabaris one drachm and a half, Praecipitate one drachm. Mix them, and reduce them to a groſs powder,</hi> With this we ſuffumigate the part, and prevent <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers</hi> in the <hi>glans.</hi>— If the Courtizan be ſo deeply infected that a ſtronger Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:46270:37"/>is requir'd when you come home you ſhall take off the <hi>Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive linnen,</hi> and take an earthen Pot with a live Coal or two, then fold a ſheet of paper round, in form of a Horn and artificially place it over the Pot: put a little Powder upon the fire, and three or four times ſuffumigate the <hi>Glans</hi> and <hi>Praepuce,</hi> having been firſt cleans'd and dry'd: <hi>&amp; tutiſſimi eritis.</hi> The Powder is this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take powder of red Roſes, Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Sandaracha rubra, of each a ſcruple and half, Benjamin, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire, Frankincenſe, of each two ſcruples, Cinnabaris</hi> 2 <hi>ſcruples. Mix them and reduce them to powder.</hi> Thus <hi>Falloppius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:46270:38"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Rudius's Prophylactique Method to prevent the Pox.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſtachius Rudius de morb. occ. &amp; venen. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. propoſes this Method. It is to be obſerv'd <hi>(ſaies he)</hi> that when any has late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convers'd with an infected wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, though as yet there appear no ſigns of infection; yet before the Venom inſinuate too far in the body, it ought to be revell'd from that part wherein 'twas firſt receiv'd, not by <hi>Erictions</hi> only, but by other <hi>Attractives</hi> which the part affected can admit and endure. Wherefore as in <hi>Contagious Diſeaſes</hi> by the <hi>Bite of Venemous Animals,</hi> a <hi>ſtrict Ligature</hi> is apply'd a little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the part affected; and then the <hi>Venom</hi> with apt <hi>Remedies</hi> is
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:46270:38"/>drawn forth. So after <hi>converſe</hi> with an <hi>infected Woman,</hi> it is not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per forthwith to take a Linnen Band of the bredth of ones finger, and ſtrictly bind the root of the Genital: which Band is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lax'd when the Patient makes water, and the part diſtends it ſelf. Then foment the whole part with a <hi>new ſponge</hi> dipt in a <hi>Lie</hi> made of twigs of <hi>Vines</hi> or <hi>Fig-tree,</hi> or in <hi>Poſea</hi> wherein has been boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſome <hi>Guaiacum,</hi> or <hi>ſharp Pickles Brine, Sea-water,</hi> or the like <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive Medicamem.</hi>— If the band wherewith the root of the genital is bound, be ſpread with a <hi>Defenſive</hi> of <hi>Bole Armeny, Maſtic, Sarcocol, fine flower</hi> and the <hi>white of an Egg,</hi> it will be far more Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent. If, after binding the part, the whole Genital be involv'd in this following Remedy, it will be moſt powerful to draw the <hi>Venom</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:46270:39"/>from the inward parts, and to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Patient.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take Guaiac 6 ounces, water</hi> 4 <hi>quarts, Boyl them until two third parts of the water be conſum'd: then add roots of wild Cucumbers, roots of Mallows, roots of Marſh mallows of each an ounce, Iberis, Thapſia of each a handful. Let the roots be bruis'd and put in; and after it has boyl'd a little, let it be remov'd from the fire, and ſtrain'd.</hi> Macerate fine linnen in this Decoction and dry it in the ſhade. After <hi>Venus</hi> having bound the root of the genital apply this defenſive linnen to the whole part: keep it bound on 2 days or more: but the Ligature at the bottom or root after the firſt day is to be taken off. Likewiſe if before <hi>Venus</hi> we uſe thoſe medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines which bind and ſtrengthen the Genital, the Venom may be kept out. <hi>Take yellow Myrobalans and Chebul Myrob. of each half an
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:46270:39"/>ounce, Cypres Nuts</hi> 15. <hi>Pine Nuts</hi> 4. <hi>red Roſe leaves a ſmall handful, Pontic Wormwood a handful, Galls, Myrtel berries, ſeeds of Sumach, of each an ounce. Let them all be bruis'd and ſteep'd in black auſtere Wine and the water of Pine-nuts, and be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill'd in a Bath.</hi> Let Linnen Rags dipt in this water warm'd be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd between the <hi>glans</hi> and <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puce:</hi> alſo herewith let the part be waſhed. For it's an <hi>excellent Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote</hi> and has often been experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally approv'd. Thus <hi>Rudius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Saxonia's Way of Prevention.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HErcules Saxonia</hi> has alſo ſet forth a <hi>Preſervative Method</hi> to prevent the <hi>Pox, cap.</hi> 16. <hi>De Due Venorea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>First, let them waſh the <hi>parts</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:46270:40"/>with <hi>ſtyptic auſtere Wine,</hi> wherein has been boyl'd <hi>Guaiac, Roſes, Myr tel-berries, Balanſtia, Acacia, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pociſtis:</hi> and after Lotion let 'em take <hi>Linnen impregnated</hi> with <hi>Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loppius's Decoction,</hi> and dry'd; and keep it on the <hi>glans.</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I much eſteem <hi>Falloppius's Decoction,</hi> yet perhaps it may be more infirm than the following one.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take Gentian, round and long Birthwort, Calamint, Dittany, Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium of Creet, Tormentil, Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, Maſterwort, of each one ounce, Scabious, Fumitary, Betony, Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, of each a handful, Wood of Aloes,</hi> 2 <hi>drachms, all three ſorts of Sanders, Raſpings of Ivory, Harts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn burnt, of each a drachm and half, Acacia, Hypociſtis, Balauſtia, Roſes, of each half an handful, Guai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acum a pound, true Muſcadel of Creet two pints, waters of Scabious, Fumitary and Roſes of each a pint,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:46270:40"/>Water of Plantain</hi> 3 <hi>pints, the beſt Praecipitate</hi> 2 <hi>drachms.</hi> Infuſe the wood in the waters and wine, and let it boyl until half be waſted; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end let the reſt of the Ingredients be put in; when they have boyl'd a little, let them ſtand in infuſion 24 hours, then boyl them until the third part be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted: when you have preſſ'd forth the Decoction, take <hi>Linnen</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion'd to the bigneſs of the <hi>glans</hi> or <hi>vulva,</hi> ſteep them in the Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and dry them in the ſhade, do ſo the ſecond and third time. This Linnen apply'd before <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> hardens the parts, dries up ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous moiſtures, hinders pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction, ſo that <hi>Falloppius</hi> has atteſted <hi>that of</hi> 1000 <hi>to whom he gave this Antidote, not one was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</hi> Nor are thoſe things to be omitted, which after <hi>Venus</hi> may conduce to the <hi>preſervation</hi> of the party: thoſe are <hi>Waſhing</hi> the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:46270:41"/>with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine</hi> or <hi>Hot water;</hi> but <hi>warm</hi> or <hi>hot Lie</hi> is better than that; and <hi>White Wine hot</hi> excells all. With this waſh not the <hi>glans</hi> only, but the whole part, as alſo the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticles, not once or twice, but of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and at leaſt two daies. But, if after <hi>Venus</hi> any have heat in their Urin, or excoriation in the <hi>glans,</hi> then ſtronger Remedies are to be us'd; the <hi>Venom</hi> is to be drawn forth, the Paſſages are to be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted that the contagion may not have paſſage to the inward parts. We muſt uſe <hi>internal Antidotes</hi> to ſubdue the Venom, and <hi>Topique Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications</hi> to draw forth the Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; as <hi>Decoctions of Dictamnus, Calamint, Scordium, Gentian, Guai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acum, made in Wine:</hi> as alſo <hi>Suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Cinnabaris, Frankincenſe, Myrrh, Wood of Aloes, Saffron.</hi> The ſame alſo is done with <hi>exenterate A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimals,</hi> as <hi>Pigeons, Chickens</hi> or the <hi>Lungs of Whelps</hi> apply'd hot to the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:46270:41"/>Privities. — If there appear no <hi>Chancre, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lceration</hi> or <hi>Inflammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> then foment it with <hi>Aqua vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae,</hi> or apply a Liniment of <hi>Venice Treacle, Mithridate,</hi> or an <hi>Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Figs, Nuts</hi> and <hi>juice of Rue</hi> — To intercept the paſſage of the Venom apply a <hi>Defenſive Oyntment</hi> to that part of the member next the belly — As concerning <hi>internal An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidotes</hi> uſe <hi>Venice Treacle, Mithri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date, Diaſcordium:</hi> and generally thoſe <hi>Antidotes</hi> which are <hi>Praeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatives</hi> againſt the <hi>Peſt</hi> are very good in this caſe — But if the Patient has the <hi>glans</hi> ulcerated or inflam'd, we are not preſently to judge it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the <hi>grand Diet-drink;</hi> for many times this accident happens immediately after <hi>impure Venus,</hi> and without dammage in any other part whatſoever.— In this caſe <hi>Praecipitate</hi> is an excellent Remedy, if duly us'd. <hi>Take of Praecipitate a drachm, of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguent. Roſ. or freſt:
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:46270:42"/>butter an ounce, mix them.</hi> Uſe this not continually, but between times uſe a <hi>warm</hi> and <hi>emollient Lotion,</hi> eſt the <hi>Praecipitate</hi> cauſe a <hi>calloſity</hi> upon the part. Therefore after 24 hours take it off, and waſh the part with a <hi>decoction of Mallows, Linſeed and a little Guaiacum:</hi> and if need require, apply the <hi>Praecipitate</hi> again.— If the body be full, purge gently with ſome <hi>Lenitive,</hi> leſt <hi>ſtrong Purges</hi> draw the Venom (which is in the outward part on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) to the inward. Forbear <hi>Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> unleſs the <hi>Chancre</hi> has an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation</hi> connex'd with it: if there is Inflammation, bleed in the foot rather than in the arm. Thus <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules Saxonia.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:46270:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Minadous his Prophylacticore.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>relius Minadous de Virulen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ Venereâ cap.</hi> 33. lays it down thus: — I return, ſays he, to the principal Deſign, propoſing the Opinion of thoſe, who believe that if after <hi>Venus</hi> the genitals were all cover'd with <hi>warm Horſe-dung,</hi> it would be a ſoveraign Remedy to prevent Infection; or rather of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table force to draw forth and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe the venom. For they believe that in that <hi>Dung</hi> there's a certain innate faculty of drawing forth and diſperſing <hi>Pockie venom.</hi> And <hi>Ioan. Coſtaeus</hi> affirms that 'tis diſcover'd by the Experiment of ſome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Phyſicians, that if one who has the <hi>Pox,</hi> cover his whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in <hi>Horſe dung,</hi> permitting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:46270:43"/>only the liberty of breathing, it will perfectly cure him. But if this Medicine can cure the body when 'tis throughly infected, how much more is it to be commended, if apply'd to the Genital only [by way of Prevention.] Thus <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadous.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> The Defenſives of Panarolus, Fraca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorius, Torrella, Cataneus, Fonſeca, Petronius, Sylvius, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PAnarolus</hi> in 's Book of <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations</hi> propoſes a Way of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting the Pox for Women with <hi>new Sponges;</hi> and he ſays 'tis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fracaſtorius</hi> bids after the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, Waſh the endanger'd part with <hi>Aq. Roſ.</hi> and then foment it <hi>decocto aluminis &amp; aerug. aeris,</hi> and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:46270:43"/>anoint that and the vicine parts with a certain <hi>Theriac <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> As for Internals he bids, give <hi>Theri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aca</hi> or <hi>Mithrid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Torrella,</hi> and out of him <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus</hi> adviſe to take an equal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of <hi>Bole-Armeny</hi> and <hi>Sang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> draconis,</hi> and with <hi>juyce of Plantain</hi> and <hi>Vinegar</hi> to be temper'd and ſpread on a linnen cloth and bound about the root of the Genital, to compreſs the Veins; and intercept the paſſage of the Venom. Then to draw forth the Poyſon, he ſcari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the lips of the <hi>Chancre,</hi> or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies <hi>Sope</hi> with <hi>Chalk:</hi> or <hi>Mithri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date;</hi> or the deplum'd Fundament of a live Pigeon to the Ulcer. And laſtly, for a <hi>Bezoartique</hi> to expel the Infection by ſweat, he gives a drachm of <hi>Theriaca</hi> in <hi>Sorrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fonſeca</hi> (<hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>Conſ.</hi> 35.) layes down the <hi>Defenſives</hi> of <hi>Falloppius, Rudius, Saxonia,</hi> &amp;c. all which
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:46270:44"/>you may ſee in the Precedent Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Petronius</hi> derides <hi>Falloppius</hi>'s <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſives,</hi> and adviſes after <hi>Venus</hi> to waſh the parts with <hi>warm <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine, Wine,</hi> or the <hi>Decoction of Guaiuc;</hi> and after waſhing to apply <hi>clean Linnen</hi> or a <hi>fine Sponge,</hi> for that extracts the <hi>Venom</hi> and <hi>infections Moiſture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joan. Sylvius (de Morbo Gallico Declam.)</hi> bids them preſently after the Act waſh the parts with <hi>warm Water,</hi> or <hi>white Wine,</hi> which is much better.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Palmarius's Defenſive Method ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily laid down. Varandous his Prophylacticon.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PAlmarius</hi> tells us that as <hi>K. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridates</hi> with his <hi>Autidate</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifi'd
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:46270:44"/>his body, and made it impaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; ſo he, deſiring the <hi>Safety</hi> of Mankind, and the <hi>Extinction</hi> of this Diſeaſe, has invented an <hi>Amulet,</hi> by the due uſe whereof Man's Body may be ſecur'd, and made impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. But withal he conjures Phyſicians not to diſcover it to lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xurious perſons. I have omitted this <hi>Amulet,</hi> becauſe of its length and my intended brevity; and alſo becauſe 'tis much ſuch another Compoſition as <hi>Theriaca Androma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi</hi> or <hi>Mithridatium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If I may be permitted to give my Opinion of <hi>Palmarius's Prophyla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticon,</hi> I judg it a <hi>potent Sudorific</hi> to cure the <hi>Pox,</hi> but not at all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per as a <hi>Defenſive</hi> to prevent the danger of this Diſeaſe. For, in our Caſe, the Blood, Humours, Inward parts, and whole Habit of the Body are all ſound and entire; the Privities onely are attaqu'd: in thoſe parts there's a <hi>ſuperficiary
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:46270:45"/>Impreſs</hi> of Venom. And certainly <hi>Internal Medicines</hi> alone can never reach the Venom when 'tis in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote part, and extrinſic ouly; but it muſt be thruſt out by <hi>Bezoartique,</hi> and drawn forth by <hi>Topique</hi> or <hi>Local Medicines.</hi> But <hi>Palmarius</hi>'s <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive Method</hi> is a tedious Preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Internal Remedies</hi> continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many days together, and in my opinion, ineffectual to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, becauſe no regard is had to the part affected.</p>
               <p>In the laſt place comes <hi>Varandae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi> This learned man in 's Book <hi>de Lue Ven.</hi> praeſcribes a Decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, much after the manner of thoſe of <hi>Falloppius</hi> and <hi>Saxonia,</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points Linnen to be macorated in it, and afterwards dry'd in the ſhade, and apply'd to the parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after <hi>Venus</hi>'s <hi>Exerciſe.</hi> He bids alſo to make water, and waſh the parts with <hi>white Wine,</hi> and to apply the <hi>Medicate Linnen</hi> or <hi>Cotton:</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:46270:45"/>impregnated with the ſame Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: as alſo to thruſt into the Uri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Paſſage the ſaid Cotton in form of a Tent. For if the <hi>Scort</hi> be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious, the Cotton in an hour or two will appear ſanious and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour'd, the filth which was in thoſe paſſages being attracted and drawn to it.— He tells us that <hi>Empiriques</hi> eſteem the following <hi>Suffiment</hi> a moſt approved thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take red Roſes, Wormwood, Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium, Dittany, red Sanders, of each a drachm, Styrax Calamita, Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaris, and Praecipitate well pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd, of each a Scruple</hi> Reduce them to a groſs powder, whereof let a little be caſt on the coals, and the ſmoak, by a ſunnel artificially plac'd on the Coals, be admitted to the genital: let the part afterwards be carefully cover'd and kept warm. Do ſo 3 mornings together. Thus <hi>Joan. Varandaeus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:46270:46"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I have now diſpatch'd the firſt part of the <hi>Expedient,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Defenſives:</hi> which I have carefully ſelected out of the <hi>learned Works</hi> of the <hi>greateſt Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> in Chriſtendome. I have communicated them chiefly for the uſe of thoſe whom the <hi>Greeks</hi> call <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> Perſons ſo furiouſly tranſported with <hi>brutiſh Deſires</hi> that they are reſolv'd to run the greateſt hazard imaginable ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than deny themſelves any <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction</hi> in that kind. But, I hope <hi>ſober perſons'</hi> will ſtill be wary, and not repoſe too much Confidence in any <hi>Defenſives</hi> whatſoever, but ſtill believe the <hi>POX</hi> a <hi>moſt perilous Diſeaſe,</hi> and in ſome Women <hi>moſt deſperately contagious. Rudius</hi> (<hi>de Morb. venen. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 10.) tells us that <hi>ſome Scorts are ſo profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poxt, that all who meddle with
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:46270:46"/>them are incurably clapt, and ſoon after diſpatcht to another World.</hi> And (<hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 8.) he tells a remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable Story of a wanton young fellow, <hi>who by kiſſing a Courtizan got ſuch a deſperate Pox upon his Tongue, that the beſt Phyſicians and Chirurgeous in the City could not cure it, but he ſoon after miſerably expir'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do really believe and avouch it that <hi>among all the Common Proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes in this Town there's ſcarce one but has the Pox.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And me thinks the very thoughs of that <hi>naſty Diſeaſe</hi> ſhould be a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to repreſs any mans deſires though never ſo impetuous.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:46270:47"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> An Expedient for rooting the Pox out of England, Tranſportation of incurable Proſtitutes propes'd, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, and urg'd from Divine Laws, and the Inſtitutes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Nations.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GEntlemen,</hi> I have faithfully diſcover'd the <hi>Secrets</hi> of <hi>this Diſeaſe:</hi> I have inſtructed you in its <hi>Cure:</hi> I have furniſh'd you with <hi>Defenſives.</hi> You are now your own Doctors; you have <hi>Excellent Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines</hi> both to <hi>prevent</hi> and <hi>cure</hi> the <hi>Pox.</hi> It only remains now that we conſider of ſome <hi>Expedient</hi> to root out this Diſeaſe, that Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men hereafter may never hear more of it. The only way to effect this, wil be to remove from this City thoſe pernicious Animals, Common
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:46270:47"/>
                  <hi>Pockie,</hi> and <hi>Incurable Proſtitutes.</hi> But you'l reply, they're ſo numerous, what ſhall we do with them all? I will propoſe an Expedient, which may be <hi>Commodious</hi> to this City: <hi>Advantageous</hi> to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Intereſt in his Plantations: and a <hi>Deſign</hi> of <hi>Charity</hi> to the <hi>Wretches</hi> themſelves: which is, to tranſport them to <hi>Jamaica</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bados.</hi> The <hi>Tranſportation</hi> of theſe <hi>Common</hi> and <hi>Incurable Courtizans,</hi> 1. Will be <hi>Commodious</hi> to this City; For, will it not be a marvellous Contentment to all, to ſee this huge <hi>City</hi> clear'd of theſe peſtilent Creatures, and to have your beds ſecur'd from the Pox? I am ſure as the caſe ſtands now, many <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Citizens</hi> are daily ruin'd by theſe women, and that not always by their own extravagancies, but too often by the debauchery of their Prentices, who uſually careſs theſe Courtizans out of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:46270:48"/>Coffers. 2. It wil be <hi>Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous</hi> to his Majeſties Plantations, which want people, and may be mightily ſupply'd and enlarg'd by the Acceſs of ſo numerous a Party, which here are wholly unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And 3. It will be a <hi>Work</hi> of <hi>Signal Charity</hi> to the <hi>Proſtitutes</hi> themſelves, to remit <hi>them</hi> and the <hi>Pox</hi> to the <hi>Indies</hi> from whence it came. For 1. It will be a work of <hi>Charity</hi> to them in reſpect of their <hi>Bodies:</hi> for this is the only way for them to attain a <hi>Speedy</hi> and <hi>Perfect Cure.</hi> Here in this cold Climate all the <hi>Art of Man</hi> is not able ever to cure them, the <hi>Pox</hi> is ſo profoundly rooted in their bones. But in thoſe hot Countries the <hi>Pox,</hi> which here could not poſſibly be overcome, has often in a fortnight been <hi>throughly cur'd,</hi> as has been experimentally atteſted by ſeveral. 2. It will be a <hi>Deſign of Charity</hi> to their <hi>Souls,</hi> to remove them from
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:46270:48"/>their <hi>curſed Company,</hi> and tranſport them to places of better <hi>Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Society.</hi> And 3. the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thoughts of <hi>Tranſportation</hi> will hereafter be ſuch a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> to <hi>luxurious women,</hi> that 'twill fright them into better manners; and probably may have greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon that numerous party than any other <hi>Menaces</hi> or <hi>Reſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Laws</hi> whatſoever.</p>
               <p>Moreover I urge this <hi>Tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> of <hi>Incurable Courtizans;</hi> 1. From the <hi>Laws of God,</hi> which command that <hi>Lepers</hi> and <hi>infected perſons</hi> ſhould be ſeparated from the reſt of Mankind. 2. From the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes</hi> and <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> of all Civil Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, who have ever us'd to ſeclude from <hi>Publique Converſe</hi> thoſe who have the <hi>Peſt, Leproſy,</hi> or <hi>other</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious Diſeaſes. Why then ſhould <hi>Pockie Strumpets</hi> be permitted the freedome of <hi>Publique Converſe,</hi> or
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:46270:49"/>liberty to infect Mankind? I am ſure <hi>Rudius</hi> and <hi>Sennertus</hi> lament the <hi>partial</hi> and <hi>uneven hand</hi> of <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Juſtice,</hi> which ſo ſeverely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes <hi>Felons,</hi> and yet permits theſe <hi>Common Scorts (ſo profoundly poxt, and beyond a poſſibility of Cure)</hi> to ruin thouſands, and infect whole <hi>Families, Cities</hi> and <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I conjure and beſeech all <hi>Good Divines,</hi> that, as I have taken <hi>Care</hi> of the <hi>Body,</hi> they would take <hi>Charge</hi> of the <hi>Soul,</hi> and by their <hi>Good Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Exemplary Lives</hi> inſtitute theſe <hi>Extravagants</hi> in the <hi>Ways</hi> of <hi>Continence</hi> and <hi>Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>ΤΕΛΟΣ.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:46270:49"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
